Edward U. Condon Papers 1920-1974 Mss.B.C752
American Philosophical Society
Edward U. Condon Papers
Circa 1920-1974
Mss.B.C752
American Philosophical Society
75.0 Linear feet
Edward Uhler Condon was a theoretical physicist at Princeton University and Westinghouse Laboratories who later served as director of the National Bureau of Standards (1945-1951), and as the director of research and development (1951-1954) and consulting physicist (1954-1974) at Corning Glass Works. The Condon Papers includes correspondence, notebooks, writings, photographs, and other materials concerning Condon's education, teaching, and his government, industrial, and academic.
75 linear feet
Condon, Edward Uhler, 1902-1974
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Alamagordo, New Mexico, on March 2, 1902, E. U. Condon spent a life in theoretical physics that brought him into many of the major developments in the field, from the quantum revolution of the 1920s to the nuclear and electronic revolution of the 1950s and 1960s. Making substantial contributions as a scientist and administrator in academia, industry, and in service to the government, Condon also tasted his fair share of controversy.
After high school, Condon initially set his sights a career in journalism, working at the Oakland Tribune during the summer of 1918 to gain experience, and continuing work on the side when he entered the University of California, Berkeley. While enrolling, dropping out, and re-enrolling from college, however, Condon discovered physics and set off on a different course. Receiving a bachelors degree with highest honors in 1924, he entered into doctoral studies at Berkeley under James Franck, and two years later, after a fevered weekend of work, produced a landmark dissertation. In this dissertation, Condon quantified the effect of light on molecular transitions and established the separability of electronic and vibrational motions in molecules which became known as the Franck-Condon principle.
Following the standard rite of passage for an American student of physics in the early 20th century, Condon accepted a National Research Council fellowship to study in Germany during the fall of 1926 and spring of 1927. Under Max Born and Arnold Sommerfeld at GC6ttingen and Munich, respectively, he applied himself to quantum theory, and after his return to the United States in 1927, took a position in public relations with Bell Telephone Laboratories.
In the spring of 1928, Condon's academic career began in earnest when he was hired as lecturer for two graduate courses at Columbia University (in quantum mechanics and the electromagnetic theory of light). His skill in interpreting the new developments in these areas earned him offers for a permanent position from six different institutions, of which he chose Princeton. He later considered the year 1928-1929 as the most productive of his academic life, capped by his work with R. W. Gurney in the development of the barrier leakage picture of alpha-particle radioactivity and quantum mechanical tunneling. Condon's and Gurney's ideas, which had been brewing simultaneously in the mind of George Gamow, represented the first application of quantum mechanics to the details of atomic structure. At Princeton, he and Philip M. Morse also produced the first English language book on quantum mechanics, Quantum Mechanics(New York: McGraw Hill, 1929).
Thus by the age of 27, Condon had earned a sufficient academic reputation to merit appointment as full professor at the University of Minnesota, though he almost immediately returned to Princeton. In this second stint at Princeton, Condon expanded his research interests to work with Gregory Breit and Richard Present on proton-proton scattering, demonstrating charge independence in the strong nuclear interaction and to early work in mass spectroscopy. His Theory of Atomic Spectra (with G.H. Shortley, 1936) is a classic in the field.
In 1937, Condon left Princeton to begin a new phase in his career -- industry -- when he accepted a position as associate director of research at Westinghouse in Pittsburgh, where he steered the corporation toward work in nuclear energy, and toward a greater emphasis on primary research. With the war looming in 1940, however, Condon moved to the Radiation Laboratory at MIT to work on air-borne radar, and in the winter 1942, was chosen by Robert Oppenheimer to help organize the secret Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, with the hopes that he would apply his experience in mass spectroscopy to the separation of uranium isotopes. Struggling with Leslie Groves, the military head of the laboratory, to maintain his civilian status, Condon returned to Westinghouse to work on microwave radar in 1943 and to the Radiation Laboratory at Berkeley to work on uranium separation.
After the war, Condon was appointed director of the National Bureau of Standards, where he created new divisions in applied mathematics and electronics which collaborated in the development of the first automatically-sequenced high-speed digital computers, and at the same time acted as science advisor to Senator Brian McMahon, chair of the special committee on atomic energy in the Senate. Condon's influence with McMahon was instrumental in the formulation of the McMahon-Douglas bill of August 1946, which established the Atomic Energy Commission, which safeguarded a civilian role in overseeing the development of nuclear energy and weaponry. His public activities drew the unwanted attention of the House Un-American Activities Commission (HUAC), which publicly accused Condon of being a liability for national security.
With the zealous prosecution of Congressman J. Parnell Thomas, head of HUAC, Condon was accused in 1952 of being "one of the weakest links in our atomic security." Condon's security clearance was questioned repeatedly, and exonerated equally often, but HUAC refused to retract its allegations. Despite the absence of evidence against him, Condon was compromised in his ability to perform at the National Bureau of Standards, and therefore resigned to become head of research at Corning Glass Works. Even this, however, did not end his troubles with HUAC. In October 1954, the Secretary of the Navy intervened to have Condon's security clearance revoked in connection with naval research being conducted at Corning. Vice President Richard Nixon hinted in campaign speeches that he had been personally involved in the suspension.
As a result of his on-going struggle with the government, Condon returned to academia, teaching at Oberlin for two years and at Washington University for seven before moving to the University of Colorado as professor of physics and fellow of the Joint Institute for Laboratory Astrophysics.
At Colorado, Condon's security clearance was restored, and he was once again consulted by the government. From 1966 to 1968, he headed a project, "the Scientific Study of Unidentified Flying Objects," undertaken at Colorado by the Air Force Office of Scientific Research to investigate claims of Unidentified Flying Objects. The "Condon Report," issued in 1968, confirmed Condon's prior skepticism with regard to UFOs, although Condon (given sole responsibility for the content of the report) and his researchers were not always in complete agreement. Nevertheless, the negative conclusion was quickly supported by the National Academy of Sciences and contributed to the decision of the Air Force to suspend Project Blue Book.
Even in the most turbulent periods of his career, Condon received the accolades of his peers. He served as president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 1953 when he was most beleaguered by HUAC, was president of the Society for Social Responsibility in Science (1968-1969), and chair of the National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (1970), and he was a member of the National Academy of Sciences (1944), the American Physical Society (President, 1946), and the American Philosophical Society (1949). He died in Boulder in 1974, leaving his wife, Emilie Honzik, and three children.
Scope and Contents note
The Papers of Edward U. Condon are comprised of correspondence, notebooks, writings, photographs, newsclippings, etc., concerning Condon's education, teaching, and his government, industrial and academic work. There is also much interesting material relating to his problems with obtaining security clearances during the late 1940s and 1950s.
The collection includes an interesting but incomplete autobiography, and there are also scattered reflections, such as his recollections of the Univ. of California, Berkeley, and Los Alamos in 1943. Some of the background material and briefs, relating to his security clearance, provide detailed biographical information.
Concerning his own writings, there are copies of many addresses, articles, books (9 boxes relating to his Handbook of Physics) and such interesting items as the Los Alamos Primer, which is a detailed technical description of the project, written for the scientists who were arriving there.
Information concerning Condon's student and teaching days includes several notebooks for physics lectures at Berkeley, 1920-1924, and there are course materials (lectures) for classes he taught in physics, atomic physics, and quantum mechanics (1931). There is a separate series of quantum mechanics lecture notes for the 1930s and 1950s.
The security clearance material is diverse, relating not only to Condon but to other scientists and to what they percevied as the more general threat posed to science. Among the more important files are those for the Eastern Industrial Personnel Security Board; the exhibits on behalf of Condon; Fowler, Levan, Hawes & Symington (legal counsel); Richard Nixon; Security Investigation; and speeches: :The Weakest Link:; U.S. Congress. House Special Committee on Un-American Activities; and U.S. Dept. of Commerce. Loyalty Board. The personal correspondence with Clifford and Virginia Durr is also rich on this topic, and on politics and social issues of the 1950s.
Condon's participation in a number of professional organizations is well, including the American Association for the Advance of Science; American Physical Society; American-Soviet Science Society; Corning Glass Works; Federation of American Scientists; SANE; Society for Social Responsibility in Science; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission; U.S. Dept. of Commerce, National Bureau of Standards (Condon was the Director); University of Colorado; Washington University; and Westinghouse Electric Corp.
Miscellaneous material of note includes folders on the Manhattan Project and an interesting journal, filed with his notebooks, kept during Operation Crossroads, the atomic bomb test conducted on Bikini Atoll on June 30, 1946. There is much on the Robert Oppenheimer case, and also a series on the President's Scientific Board, 1947.
Series I. Correspondence, 1931-1991 (7 boxes; 3.25 linear feet)
Series II. Notebooks and diaries, 1922-1946 (3 boxes; 1.25 linear feet)
Series III. Miscellaneous materials, 1936-1971 (1 box; 0.5 linear feet)
Series IV. Photographs (1 box; 0.5 linear feet)
Series V. UFO materials (33 boxes; 16.5 linear feet)
Series VI. Printed materials (11 boxes; 5.5 linear feet)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Condon Papers were deposited at the APS Library by the Estate of Edward Uhler Condon in 1974.
Separated Materials note
Printed materials have been transferred to the Printed Materials Department, and can be located through the Library's OPAC, VOLE, and are noted as being "From the estate of E. U. Condon." Please consult a librarian for assistance.
Related Archival Materials note
The APS houses several collections that document the history of the development of the atomic bomb, including the papers of Henry DeWolf Smyth, Stanislaw M. Ulam, and John A. Wheeler for the physics of A-bomb development, and Curt Stern and James V. Neel relating to the genetics. The APS also houses two collections relating to the investigation of UFO sightings, namely the papers of Philip J. Klass, and Donald Howard Menzel.
American Association for the Advancement of Science.; American Physical Society.; American-Soviet Science Society.; Bethe, Hans A., (Hans Albrecht), 1906-2005; Birge, Raymond T., (Raymond Thayer), 1887-1980; Boas, Ernst P., (Ernst Philip), 1891-1955; Branscomb, Lewis M., 1926-; Breit, Gregory, 1899-1981; Briggs, Lyman J., (Lyman James), 1874-1963; Bronk, Detlev W., (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Chubb, Lewis Warrington, b. 1882; Compton, Arthur Holly, 1892-1962; Corning Glass Works.; Courant, Richard, 1888-1972; David, Nathan H.; DuBridge, Lee A., (Lee Alvin), 1901-1994; Durr, Clifford J., (Clifford Judkins), 1899-1975; Durr, Virginia Foster; Eastern Industrial Personnel Security Board.; Federation of American Scientists.; Fowler, Levan, Hawes & Symington.; Gamow, George, 1904-1968; Gurney-Taylor, Natalie; Kamen, Martin David, 1913-; Loeb, Leonard B., (Leonard Benedict), 1891-1978; Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory.; Menzel, Donald Howard, 1901-1976; Meyerhoff, Howard A., (Howard Augustus), 1899-; Morley, Robert H.; Newman, James Roy, 1907-1966; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-; Norberg, Richard E.; Oppenheimer, Frank, 1912-; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967; Pake, G. E., (George Edward); Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994; Phelps, John B., 1929-; Phillips, Melba, 1907-; Rabi, I. I., (Isidor Isaac), 1898-1988; Roberts, Walter O., 1915-; SANE, Inc.; Seitz, Frederick, 1911-; Shortley, George, 1910; Society for Social Responsibility in Science (ACT).; Teller, Edward, 1908-2003; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers. Manhattan District..; United States. Atomic Energy Commission; United States. Department of Commerce. Loyalty Board; United States. National Bureau of Standards.; University of California, Berkeley.; University of Colorado, Boulder.; Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981; Veblen, Oswald, 1880-1960; Visscher, Maurice B., 1901-; Washington University (Saint Louis, Mo.).; Weaver, Warren, 1894-1978; Westinghouse Electric Corporation.; Atomic bomb--United States; Autobiographies.; Bikini Atoll (Pacific Islands); Journals (notebooks); Lectures; Notebooks; Nuclear physics--Research--United States; Nuclear weapons--Testing; Operation Crossroads, 1946; Photoprints; Physics--Research--United States; Physics--Study and teaching; Quantum theory; Speeches.; United States--Politics and government--1945-
- Series I. Correspondence, 1920-1974; 128 boxes, 64 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists mainly of correspondence to Condon, arranged alphabetically. The Series also contains various papers, addresses, and drafts of works by Condon and others.
  - Abbott, Mary K. (Box 1)
  - Abelson, Philip H. - Science in the Seventies (Box 1)
  - Abrams, Jill (Box 1)
  - Academic Press, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Academy for Educational Development, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Academy of Science of St. Louis (Box 1)
  - Academy of Sciences, U.S.S.R. (Box 1)
  - Acree, S. F. (Box 1)
  - AD-X2 Battery Additive Case, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company (Box 1)
  - Adomian, George (Box 1)
  - Agnew, Spiro T. (Box 1)
  - Agronsky, Martin (Box 1)
  - Aharonov, Yakir - Time Symmetry in the Quantum Process of Measurement (Box 1)
  - Ahmedabad Textile Industry's Research Association (Box 1)
  - Air Pollution (Box 1)
  - Albert, Frieda (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Sam[uel] N. (Box 1)
  - Alexander, William M. (Box 1)
  - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Alfred University (Box 1)
  - All Saints' Episcopal Church [Chevy Chase, Md.] (Box 1)
  - Allen, Alex (Box 1)
  - Allen, Dean A. (Box 1)
  - Allen, Harper (Box 1)
  - Allied Chemical and Dye Corporation. The Solvay Process Division. (Box 1)
  - Allison, David (Box 1)
  - Almond, Stephen W. (Box 1)
  - Alpha Chi Sigma (Box 1)
  - Alsop, Joseph (Box 1)
  - Alvarez, Luis W. (Box 1)
  - Aly, Hadi H. (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Bulletin, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 46 folders (Box 1-2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science. Publications Committee (Box 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - British Association for the Advancement of Science. Science and the Future. April 13-19, 1969, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - British Association for the Advancement of Science. Science.... Miscellany, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science - British Association for the Advancement of Science. Science.... Papers, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - American Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities (Box 2)
  - American Association of Physics Teachers, 11 folders (Box 3)
  - American Association of Scientific Workers (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box 3)
  - American Ceramic Society, Inc. (Box 3)
  - American Chemical Society, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - American Committee for Emigré Scholars, Writers and Artists, Inc. (Box 3)
  - American Committee for the Weizmann Institute of Science (Box 3)
  - American Congress on Surveying and Mapping (Box 3)
  - American Friends Fellowship Council, and Friends World Committee, American Section (Box 3)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - American Geophysical Union (Box 3)
  - American Institute of Chemical Engineers (Box 3)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers (Box 3)
  - American Institute of France (Box 3)
  - American Institute of Physics, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - American Journal of Physics (Box 3)
  - American Philosophical Society, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - American Physical Society, 26 folders (Box 4)
  - American Russian Institute (Box 4)
  - American Scholar (Box 4)
  - American Society for Engineering Education (Box 4)
  - American Society for Metals (Box 4)
  - American Society for Quality Control, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - American Society for Technion (Box 4)
  - American Society for Testing Materials (Box 4)
  - American Society for the Advancement of the Hebrew Institute of Technology in Haifa, Palestine (Box 4)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers (Box 4)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (Box 4)
  - American-Soviet Friendship, Inc., 3 folders (Box 4)
  - American-Soviet Science Society, 24 folders (Box 5)
  - American Standards Association (Box 5)
  - American Statistical Association (Box 5)
  - American University (Box 5)
  - American Veterans Committee (Box 5)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (Box 5)
  - Amlauer, Karl (Box 5)
  - Ancizar-Sordo, Jorge (Box 5)
  - Anderson, David L. (Box 5)
  - Anderson, David L. The Electronic Charge and Avogadro's Number (Box 5)
  - Anderson Kramer Associates, Inc. (Box 5)
  - Ando, Tsuyoshi. Properties of Fermion Density Matrices, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Annual Reviews, Inc., 27 folders (Box 5-6)
  - Anslow, W. Parker, Jr. (Box 6)
  - Anti-Ballistic Missile - Point of No Return? (Box 6)
  - Anti-Ballistic Missile System, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Aranow, R. H. - Radiocarbon Dating: The Nitrogen Error (Box 6)
  - Argonne National Laboratory (Box 6)
  - Armistead, William H., 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Armour Research Foundation (Box 6)
  - Armstrong Cork Company (Box 6)
  - Armstrong, Lloyd (Box 6)
  - Armstrong, Richard A. (Box 6)
  - Army Medical Center (Box 6)
  - Arnberg, Carl Oscar (Box 6)
  - Arnold, Fortas & Porter, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Arnold, Samuel, 3rd (Box 6)
  - Arnott, E. G. F. (Box 6)
  - Arons, Arnold (Box 6)
  - Aronson (Box 6)
  - Ashby, Lyle W. (Box 6)
  - Ashby, N. Report on Feasibility Study on Solar Heating of Denver Community College North Campus Classroom Building. (Box 6)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies (Box 6)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies. Report, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Association for Computing Machinery (Box 6)
  - Association of Los Alamos Scientists (Box 6)
  - Association of Pittsburgh [PA] Scientists (Box 6)
  - Association of World Colleges and Universities (Box 6)
  - Astin, Allen V. (Box 6)
  - Astin, Margaret [Mrs. Allen V.] (Box 6)
  - Astronomical Society of the Pacific (Box 6)
  - Atchison, F. Stanley (Box 6)
  - Atkins, Kenneth R. (Box 6)
  - Atomic Energy, 55 folders (Box 6-7)
  - Atomic Energy. Ban of Nuclear Weapons, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Atomic Energy. Chronological Highlights of the Atomic Bomb Project. (Box 7)
  - Atomic Energy. Congressional Legislation, 1945, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Atomic Energy. Congressional Legislation, 1946, 15 folders (Box 7-8)
  - Atomic Energy. Congressional Legislation, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Congressional Legislation, 1954, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Control Conference, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Control - International, 17 folders (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Essential Information on ... (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Glossary of Important Terms in Nuclear Physics. (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Operation Crossroads, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. Suspension of Tests., 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. United Nations Atomic Energy Commission. Report to the Security Council, Sept. 1947 (Box 8)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Congressional Hearings, May 1949 (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Congressional Hearings, June 1949, 15 folders (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Congressional Hearings, July 1949, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. House. Hearings, Oct. 1945 (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. House. Hearings, May, June 1963, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Bills for the Development and Control of Atomic Energy. (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Hearings, Dec. 1945, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Hearings, Jan. 1946, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Hearings, Feb. 1946, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Hearings, Apr. 1946 (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Hearings, May 1949 (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Hearings, June 1959 (Box 9)
  - Atomic Energy. U.S. Senate. Special Committee on Atomic Energy, 22 folders (Box 9-10)
  - Atomic Energy. The United States Strategic Bombing Survey. The Effects of Atomic Bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki. (Box 10)
  - Atomic Energy. University of Chicago Metallurgical Laboratory, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 10)
    See: U. S. Atomic Energy Commission
  - Atomic Energy Documentation Service, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Atomic Energy of Canada, Ltd. (Box 10)
  - Atomic Magnitudes, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Atomic Structure (Encycl. Brit.), 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Augsburg College (Box 10)
  - Auton, Jesse (Box 10)
  - Auville, René (Box 10)
  - B- - - - -, Sandy (Box 10)
  - Bacher, Robert F. (Box 10)
  - Bacher, Robert F. The Hydrogen Bomb (Box 10)
  - Bailey, Joyce (Box 10)
  - Bainbridge, K. T. (Box 10)
  - Baja California Astronomical Observatory (Box 10)
  - Baker, C. L. (Box 10)
  - Ball, William P. (Box 10)
  - Baring, John A. (Box 10)
  - Barry, Mrs. Scammon (Box 10)
  - Barth, Alan (Box 10)
  - Barth, C. A. L. Wallace, and J. B. Pearce. Mariner 5 - Measurement of Lyman Alpha Radiation on Venus (Box 10)
  - Barton, Henry A. (Box 10)
  - Baruch, Bernard M. (Box 10)
  - Barut, A. O. Calculation of Relativistic Transition Probabilities and Form Factors from Non-Compact Groups (Box 10)
  - Barut, A. O. Current Operators and Majorana Equation for the Hydrogen Atom from Dynamical Groups (Box 10)
  - Barut, A. O. The Nature of the Nuclear Bond and the Structure of Hadrons (Box 10)
  - Basic Books, Inc., 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Bates, A. Allan, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Battelle Memorial Institute (Box 10)
  - Beadle, George W. (Box 10)
  - Beams, J. W. (Box 10)
  - Beane, Don (Box 10)
  - Beaser, Herbert Wilton (Box 10)
  - Beaty, Earl C. (Box 10)
  - Beck, Donald Richardson, 5 folders (Box 10)